# Shubham Tiwari

## PhD student, University of Washington

# **Research Interests**

Broadly interested in the intersection of distributed systems and machine learning. My current focus is on efficient LLM serving via workload-aware, tiered KVCache management. Previously, I have worked on a broad spectrum of problems – memory management optimizations in hypervisors, network measurement, and congestion control (LEOScope, iBox).

## Education

**University of Washington**, *Seattle* Sept 2023 - Present

Ph.D. in Computer Science (ongoing) Advisors: Simon Peter, Ratul Mahajan

Birla Institute of Technology and Science (BITS), Pilani Aug 2016 - July 2021

B.E. Computer Science and M.Sc. Mathematics Thesis: Data-Driven Network Simulation with iBox

# Experience

Microsoft Research, Redmond June 2024 - Sept 2024

Research Intern with Ishai Menache

Project: Improvements to Azure Compute's VM allocation service.

Microsoft Research, Bangalore Aug 2021 - Aug 2023

Research Fellow with Debopam Bhattacherjee, Venkat Padmanabhan

<u>Projects</u>: LEO Satellite Networks (<u>LEOScope</u>)

Microsoft Research, Bangalore Jan 2021 - July 2021

Research Intern with Venkat Padmanabhan, Nagarajan Natarajan

<u>Project</u>: Data-Driven Network Simulation (<u>iBox</u>)

VMware, Bangalore Aug 2020 - Dec 2020

*Intern, xLabs with Jayneel Gandhi* 

**Project:** Page-table Replication (Mitosis)

Samsung Research, Bangalore May 2020 - July 2020

Research Intern

Project: Cellular Network Planning

Software-Defined Networking Lab, BITS Pilani Jan 2019 - Dec 2019

Research Assistant with K. Hari Babu

<u>Project</u>: Passive Estimation of Link Latency (qMon)

### **Publications**

C=Conference, J=Journal, P=Preprint, A=Article

### A.1 LEOScope: Building a Global Testbed for Low-Earth Orbit Satellite Networks

Saeed Fadaei, <u>Shubham Tiwari</u>, Aryan Taneja, Saksham Bhushan, Mohamed Kassem, Aravindh Raman, Debopam Bhattacherjee, Lili Qiu, Alan Woodward, Nishanth Sastry

SIGCOMM Computer Communication Review [nominated for Best of CCR]

SIGCOMM CCR'25

#### C.1 Boosting Application Performance using Heterogeneous Virtual Channels: Challenges and Opportunities

Talal Touseef, William Sentosa, Milind Kumar Vaddiraju, Debopam Bhattacherjee, Balakrishnan Chandrasekaran, Brighten Godfrey, Shubham Tiwari

 $22^{nd}$  ACM Workshop on Hot Topics in Networks

HotNets'23

#### P.1 T3P: Demystifying Low-Earth Orbit Satellite Broadband

Shubham Tiwari, Saksham Bhushan, Aryan Taneja, Mohamed Kassem, Cheng Luo, Cong Zhou, Zhiyuan He, Aravindh Raman, Nishanth Sastry, Lili Qiu, Debopam Bhattacherjee

**Preprint** 

#### C.2 Simulating Network Paths with Recurrent Buffering Units

Divyam Anshumaan, Sriram Balasubramanian, <u>Shubham Tiwari</u>, Nagarajan Natarajan, Sundararajan Sellamanickam, and Venkata N. Padmanabhan

 $37^{th}$  AAAI Conference on Artificial Intelligence

AAAI'23

#### C.3 Data-Driven Network Path Simulation with iBox

Sachin Ashok, <u>Shubham Tiwari</u>, Nagarajan Natarajan, Venkata N. Padmanabhan, and Sundararajan Sellamanickam *ACM SIGMETRICS / IFIP PERFORMANCE 2022* SIGMETRICS'22

#### J.1 qMon: A method to monitor queueing delay in OpenFlow networks

Sandhya Rathee, <u>Shubham Tiwari</u>, K Haribabu, and Ashutosh Bhatia *Journal of Communications and Networks* 

ICN'22

# **Projects**

ElasticCache: Efficient LLM Serving via Workload-aware, Tiered KVCache Management Advisors: Simon Peter, Ratul Mahajan

April 2024 - Present

- > Developing a workload-aware serving system that profiles LLM workflows to determine cache access patterns for efficient utilization of tiered, disaggregated KVCache.
- > Working on building a prototype (scheduler + tiered KVCache) on top of vLLM to evaluate our techniques on various LLM workflows and traffic patterns.

#### Optimizations to Azure Compute's VM Allocation Service

June 2024 - Sept 2024

Advisors: Ishai Menache

- > Evaluated the impact of enabling fine-grained VM placement strategies at scale.
- > Proposed changes to resource allocation service with the potential of saving (> \$1M) in operational costs.

## LEOScope: Enabling Experimentation Across Low-Earth Orbit (LEO) Satellite Networks

July 2022 - Present

Advisors: Debopam Bhattacherjee, Venkat Padmanabhan [code]

- > Lead an effort with **Azure Space**, **MSRA**, and academic collaborators to build a platform of a global scale for experimentation across Low-Earth Orbit Satellite networks.
- > Drove the effort through engineering challenges such as platform architecture, implementation of experiment scheduler, executor, and the central orchestrator.
- > Initiated large-scale measurements based on ping and iperf to characterize satellite network paths.

iBox: Internet in a Box
Advisors: Venkat Padmanabhan, Nagarajan Natarajan [website]

Jan 2021 - June 2022

- > Built a data-driven network simulator that uses data to recreate end-to-end behavior of a network path.
- > Leveraged a combination of internet measurement data and ML models to capture the impact of complex network phenomena such as cross-traffic and packet reordering.
- > Integrated iBox with ns-2, ns-3, netem and Microsoft Teams's in-house network simulator.
- > Resulting papers published at SIGMETRICS'22 and AAAI'23.

#### qMon: Passive Delay Monitoring in SDNs

Jan 2019 - Dec 2019

Advisor: K. Hari Babu [paper] [code]

- > Devised **qMon**, a scalable latency monitoring technique with zero data plane footprint.
- > Developed an Open vSwitch based prototype to fetch queue length information using OpenFlow and passively estimate link latency.
- > Evaluated qMon on a physical testbed under various traffic scenarios.
- > Resulting paper published at JCN 2022.

### Mitosis: Enabling Page-Table Replication in ESXi

Aug 2020 - Dec 2020

Advisor: Jayneel Gandhi

- > Implemented page-table replication (Mitosis) in VMware's core virtualization product ESX.
- > Developed prototypes to disambiguate the design and code needed to support page table replication in the ESX kernel.
- > Conducted workload profiling to estimate the performance benefits of page-table replication; realized gains of upto 17% in workload execution time.

# Miscellaneous

- > Demonstrated iBox at TAB MSR India's annual technical event.
- > Presented iBox at SIGMETRICS'22. [video]
- > Awarded a grant of 50,000 INR by AUGSD, BITS Pilani for developing a miniature autonomous driving vehicle.